A Guide to the Carter/Cash Family Collection, c.1940-2009
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Carter/Cash Family Collection c.1940-2009
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2009-090
1.0 cu. ft.; 1 box
The Carter/Cash Family Collection contains memoirs, biographies, photographs, funeral programs, newspaper and magazine articles, and memorabilia relating to the Carter family and Johnny Cash.
Collector
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The initial materials for the Carter/Cash Family Collection were purchased by Special Collections in June 2009. Additional materials were purchased by Special Collections in two further accruals during July and August 2009.
Biographical/Historical Information
In the early 1900s, "hillbilly" music was being recorded in studios in northern states. The distance from the mountains of Tennessee and Virginia made it difficult for musicians to record their music. Ralph Peer–a producer for Victor Talking Machine Company in Bristol, Tennessee–decided to take advantage of this booming genre of music by establishing a recording studio on the second floor of the Taylor-Christian Hat Company on State Street in Bristol. In 1927, Peer recorded several songs with musicians that, to this day, are still regarded as the mothers and fathers of country music. Ralph Peer is also credited with discovering Jimmie Rodgers–one of country music's legends–at the Bristol Sessions.
In response to Peer's call for musicians, Alvin Pleasant "A.P." Delaney Carter, his wife, Sara Doughtery Carter, and his sister-in-law, Maybelle Kilgore Addington Carter traveled to Bristol to record their music. The Carter Family recorded six songs and soon became known as the "first family" of country music. The Carter Family continued to grow in size and musical talent. Maybelle Carter and her husband Ezra (A.P's brother) were the parents of June (1929-2003), Helen (1927-1998), and Anita (1933-1999), who later performed as the Carter Sisters. Although Johnny Cash (1932-2003) was, arguably, one of the most influential country music artists of all time, his music broke the boundaries of traditional country music, spilling over into other genres including blues, gospel, and rock and roll. Since his marriage to June Carter in 1968, he has been considered a member of the Carter family musicians.
For additional information on the Carter and Cash families, see:
Birthplace of Country Music website.
Streissguth, Micheal. Johnny Cash: The Biography. Cambridge, MA: Da Cape Press, 2006.
Newman Library 3rd Floor ML 420 .C265 S66 2006
Zwonitzer, Mark. Will You Miss Me When I'm Gone?: The Carter Family and Their Legacy in American Music. New York: Simon & Schuster, c2002.
Newman Library 3rd Floor ML 421 .C33 Z86 2002/Special Collections Rare Book Collection ML 421 .C33 Z86 2002 c.2 Spec Large
Scope and Content
The Carter/Cash Family Collection contains memoirs written by Janette Carter and Gladys Millard (daughters of A.P. and Sara), biographies, discographies, sheet music, and a compact disc recording titled The Original Carter Family in Texas (1999). In addition to this material, the collection includes programs from the Carter Family Memorial Festival and Craft Show (2000, 2002-2004, and 2008), funeral services for second generation Carter musicians and Johnny Cash, and special events at the Carter Family Fold. The Carter/Cash Family Collection also contains photographs, newspaper and magazine articles, and memorabilia, such as Maybelle's hunting and fishing license (1975) and a Carter Fold volunteer badge.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series–Series I: Memoirs and Biographies, Series II: Memorabilia, and Series III: Newspaper and Magazine Articles.
Series I: Memoirs and Biographies, 1980-2005, n.d. This series includes two memoirs written by Janette Carter (1983, 2005). The earliest of these two memoirs is autographed by Janette and Joe Carter, and the more recent memoir is autographed by Janette Carter, Flo (A.P. and Sara's first grandchild, the daughter of Gladys) and Johnny Wolfe (Flo's husband), and Dale (Janette's son) and Teresa Jett (Dale's wife). This series also contains a memoir written about A.P. Carter by Gladys Millard (n.d.), as well as a collection of Carter Family sheet music with a biography written by Johnny Cash (1980). This series is arranged chronologically.
Series II: Memorabilia, 1941-2008, n.d. This series is comprised primarily of items relating to the Carter family's music, programs of events involving the family, and photographs. The series has been divided into the following five sub-series:
Sub-series 1: Discographies, n.d. This sub-series includes two discographies of the Carter Sisters and Mother Maybelle, one of which includes performances with Chet Atkins. It is likely that these discographies were meant to accompany audio recordings of the listed songs. This sub-series is arranged by material type.
Sub-series 2: Music, 1944-1999, n.d. This sub-series includes two books of sheet music (1944, n.d.) and a compact disc recording titled The Original Carter Family in Texas (1999). This sub-series is arranged by material type.
Sub-series 3: Programs, 2000-2008, n.d. This sub-series includes programs from the 26th, 28th, 29th, 30th, and 34th Annual Carter Family Memorial Festival and Craft Show (2000, 2002-2004, 2008), as well as the Carter Fold performance schedule for May and June of 2003. This sub-series also contains programs from the dedication ceremony for the A.P. Carter Cabin (2004) and the Janette Carter Memorial Gospel Concert (2008). In addition to event programs, this Sub-series also includes funeral programs for June Carter Cash (2003), Johnny Cash (2003), Joe D. Carter (2005), and Janette Carter (2006). This sub-series is arranged chronologically within each event type.
Sub-series 4: Photographs, 2002, n.d. This subseries includes a photograph of the original Carter Family (n.d.), a small portrait of Maybelle (n.d.), a small picture of Janette performing (1965), and five photographs taken at the Carter Fold - one of Johnny Cash, two of June Carter Cash (2002), one of Joe and Janette (2002), and one of June, John Carter Cash, and Rosanne Cash (2001). This subseries is arranged chronologically. This series also contains five photographs of Helen Carter (n.d.), a picture of Sara, Coy Bayes, and Gladys Millard (n.d.), and two pictures of Janette Carter and friends (n.d.). This sub-series is arranged chronologically, with the undated material last.
Sub-series 5: Miscellaneous, c.1940-2004, n.d. This sub-series includes Sara Carter's Musicians' Protective Association Card (c.1940), Maybelle Carter's hunting and fishing license (1975), and a scrapbook page dated May 29, 2004, that features a magazine clipping of the original Carter Family that is signed by Carlene Carter (June's daughter), Connie Smith, and John Carter Cash (Johnny and June's son). In addition, this sub-series also includes A.P.'s "Bible Questions and Answers" booklet (n.d.), Maybelle's Holiday Inn "Inner Circle" card (n.d.), a Carter Fold volunteer badge (n.d.), and a collectible seat cushion from the Carter Fold (n.d.). This sub-series is arranged by material type.
Series III. Newspaper and Magazine Articles, 1991-2009. This series includes nine newspaper articles from the Kingsport, Tennessee, Times News, as well as three GoTricities special publications from the Times News. The series also includes two newspaper articles from the Bristol Herald Courier and one special supplemental publication from the Scott County, Virginia, Star. Although most of these articles discuss the public response to the death of Joe D. Carter, Janette Carter, June Carter Cash, and Johnny Cash, some discuss the impact of the Carter Family in their respective communities, as well as the country music genre. This series also contains an issue of Life that celebrates the life of A.P. Carter and an issue of People that pays tribute to Johnny Cash. This series is arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
The following books have been removed cataloged for the Special Collections Rare Book Collection:
Cash, June Carter. Among My Klediments. Grand Rapids: Zondervan Publishing House, 1979.
Rare Book Collection ML 420 .C2653 A3 c.2 Spec Large
Wolfe, Charles K., June Carter Cash, Johnny Cash, A. P. Carter, Sara Carter, Maybelle Carter, and Jimmie Rodgers. The Carter Family: In the Shadow of Clinch Mountain. [Hambergen, Germany]: Bear Family Records, 2000.
Rare Book Collection ML 394 .C3 W65 2000 Spec Large
Zwonitzer, Mark and Charles Hirshberg. Will You Miss Me When I'm Gone?: The Carter Family and Their Legacy in American Music. New York: Simon & Schuster, c2002.
Rare Book Collection ML 421 .C33 Z86 2002 c.2 Spec Large
Index Terms
Persons:
Carter, A. P. (Alvin Pleasant), 1891-1960.; Carter, Anita.; Carter, Helen, 1927-1998.; Carter, Janette.; Carter, Joe, 1927-2005.; Carter, Maybelle, 1909-1978.; Carter, Sara, 1898-1979.; Cash, Johnny.; Cash, June Carter, 1929-2003.
Family Names:
Carter Family (Musical group).
Subjects:
Country musicians--United States.; Country musicians--United States--Biography.; Carter Sisters.
Genre and Form Terms:
Articles.; Biographies.; Discographies.; Programs.
Occupations:
Country musicians.
Contents List
- Series I: Memoirs and Biographies, 1980-2005, n.d.
  - The Original Carter Family. New York: Peer International Corporation, 1980. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Carter, Janette. Living with Memories. Hiltons, VA: Carter Family Memorial Music Center, 1983. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Carter, Janette. My Clinch Mountain Home. Hiltons, VA: Carter Family Memorial Music Center, 2005. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Millard, Gladys. "I Remember Daddy."Sunny Side Sentinel. Carter Family Fan Club, n.d. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Series II: Memorabilia, 1941-2008, n.d.
  - Sub-series 1: Discographies, n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - "The Carter Sisters and Mother Maybelle: Their Complete Recordings," n.d.
    - "The Carter Sisters and Mother Maybelle with Chet Atkins: Ozark Radio," n.d.
  - Sub-series 2: Music, 1944-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - The Carter Family Album of Smokey Mountain Ballads. New York: Southern Music Company, Inc., 1944.
    - McMurray, Vance. Original Hill and Country Songs. Gate City, VA: Vance McMurray, n.d.
    - The Original Carter Family in Texas. Brighton, MI: Old Homestead Records, 1999.
  - Sub-series 3: Programs, 2000-2008, n.d.
    - Annual Carter Family Memorial Festival and Craft Show, 2000, 2002-2004, 2008. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Carter Fold Performance Schedule, 2003. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Funeral programs for June Carter Cash, Johnny Cash, Joe D. Carter, and Janette Carter, 2003, 2005-2006. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Dedication of A.P. Carter Cabin, 2004. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Memorial Service Program, Janette Carter, c.2006. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Janette Carter Memorial Gospel Concert, 2008. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Sub-series 4: Photographs, 2002, n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Janette Carter (3), 1965, n.d.
    - June Carter Cash, John Carter Cash, and Rosanne Cash, 2001.
    - Joe and Janette Carter, 2002.
    - Johnny Cash at Carter Fold, 2002.
    - June Carter Cash at Carter Fold (2), 2002.
    - Helen Carter (5), n.d.
    - Sara Carter, Coy Bayes, and Gladys Carter Millard, n.d.
    - The Original Carter Family, n.d.
    - Maybelle Carter, n.d.
  - Sub-series 5: Miscellaneous, c.1940-2009, n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Sara Carter's Musicians' Protective Association Card, c.1940.
    - Maybelle Carter's Hunting and Fishing License, 1975.
    - Maybelle Carter's Holiday Inn "Inner Circle" Card, n.d.
    - A.P. Carter's "Bible Questions and Answers" Booklet, n.d.
    - Collectible seat cushion, n.d.
    - Carter Fold Volunteer Badge, n.d.
    - Scrapbook page, 2004.
- Series III: Newspaper and Magazine Articles, 1991-2009.
  - Life magazine article about A.P. Carter, December 1991. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Bristol Herald Courier, Special Section, July 24, 2002. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - GoTricities special publication, Kingsport, Tennessee, Times News, July 26-August 1, 2002. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Bristol Herald Courier, May 16, 2003. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Kingsport, Tennessee, Times News articles, May-September, 2003. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - People magazine article, September 29, 2003. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Supplemental publication for Scott County, Virginia, Star, August 4, 2004. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Kingsport, Tennessee, Times News articles and GoTricities special publications, 2004-2009. (Box-folder 1:13)